Let's start with a question: what is a complex number, really
On paper we write a complex number as a + bi
But don't let the letters distract you — this is simply a point in the plane
So the first thing we do is treat a + bi as an arrow from the origin to the point (a
The horizontal axis is the real axis, the vertical is the imaginary axis
The number a + bi is the arrow
Now that arrow gives us immediate geometric language
Adding complex numbers is just vector addition
If I take a + bi
place the arrow for c + di at the tip of the arrow for a + bi
draw the diagonal — that diagonal is a + bi + (c + di)
So addition is translation
Nothing magical — it's the same geometry as adding displacement vectors
Multiplication is where the plane reveals a richer, more interesting structure
What does it mean to multiply complex numbers
Let's build intuition slowly
First, multiplying by a real number stretches or shrinks the arrow
Multiply by 2, the arrow doubles in length; multiply by 0
5, it halves
So real scaling is radial scaling
But what about multiplying by i
Every point on the plane is multiplied by i: the entire plane rotates 90 degrees counterclockwise
Every arrow rotates without changing its length
So i acts like a 90-degree rotation operator
Multiplication by -1 flips the arrow 180 degrees
Multiplying by -i rotates 90 degrees clockwise
So multiplication
does two things: it scales lengths
rotates directions
We can capture that neatly by switching to polar coordinates
Any nonzero complex number z can be written as r e to the i theta
where r is the length (|z|)
theta is the angle the arrow makes with the real axis (arg z)
In these terms
multiplication becomes obvious: (r1 e to the i theta1) times (r2 e to the i theta2) = (r1 r2) e to the i (theta1 + theta2)
Multiplying multiplies radii and adds angles
This polar expression is tightly tied to Euler's formula
e to the i theta = cos theta + i sin theta
So an exponential with an imaginary exponent traces out a circle as theta varies
As theta increases linearly
the point moves around a circle centered at the origin
Now that we can multiply
think in terms of scaling
a whole family of visual phenomena becomes easy to understand
Powers: raise a number to a power n
In polar form, (r e to the i theta) to the n = r to the n e to the i n theta
So raising to the second power squares the radius and doubles the angle
Let's look at a grid under the map z maps to z squared
Points with different radii accelerate apart because radii are squared
angles are doubled so every petal